Guide to the Yale Collection of German Literature Manuscript Miscellany
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Yale Collection of German Literature manuscript miscellany
1700-2009
YCGL MSS MISC
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts, including literary manuscripts, letters, and other documents. Materials are grouped under headings by author or corporate name.
Total Boxes: ongoing
Linear Feet: ongoing
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Source information is recorded on the folders. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts acquired by the Beinecke Library from various sources and at various times, which the Library has chosen to describe here rather than as separate entries in Yale University Library's on-line Public Access Catalog (Orbis). These materials include literary manuscripts, individual or small groups of letters, and single documents. Materials are grouped under headings for author or other personal or corporate name to which they most closely relate. Items of unidentified authorship are grouped separately under "Unidentified" at the end of the finding aid. Group numbers were assigned to headings in an initial alphabetical sequence and thereafter in order of processing; within each group, folders (F-[#]) and volumes (V-[#]) are numbered in order of processing.
To request materials listed here, please cite the miscellany call number, YCGL MSS MISC, the group number, and the folder or volume number appearing to the left of the item description. For example, to obtain item F-1 from the materials listed under Max Brod, complete an individual call slip as follows:
YCGL MSS MISC
Grp 5, item F-1
This list is ongoing, and it is subject to revision as new materials are acquired and, on occasion, as groups of manuscripts are removed and cataloged separately as artificial collections. When materials are removed and reclassified, a cross reference to the new call number is placed in the list. In addition to newly received items, which have been described using current cataloging standards, this finding aid contains previously cataloged material. Descriptions for the latter items have been transcribed from card sets in the Manuscript Catalog.
Authors, German; German literature; Photographs; Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- A
  - ADLER, H. G.
    - Poems, undated; Adler, H. G., 1910-1988; 11 items. (Box GROUP 36, Folder F-1)
      Scope and Contents
      Poems, typescript carbon, with a few manuscript corrections. Poems are titled: "Ankunft bis hierher," "Tief ins Gedächtnis gehängt," "Wie ist es zu fassen: wir sind dabei," "Dies einmal sagen," "Du, dein ganzes Gesetz," "Glückliche Reise," "Verheissung aus Gedächtnis und Stillstand," "Dies gilt und bleibt immer vergangen," "Das Moos der Trauer," "Im Anfang schuf," and "Wohin? was wir uns erwarten."
      General note
      Accession: 20000706-j
  - ANTON ULRICH, HERZOG VON BRAUNSCHWEIG-WOLFENBÜTTEL, 1633-1714
    - Note: Braunschweig, 1708 Aug 7; Ulrich, Antonio, Herzog von Braunschweig-Wolfenbüttel, 1633-1714; 1 item (1 p.); 10 x 16 cm. (Box GROUP 12, Folder F-1)
      ANS: "Die Closterstube kan hievon eyne Verordnung machen."
- B
  - BINDING, RUDOLF GEORG, 1867-1938
    - Letter: Starnberg, to Kurt von Faber du Faur, [19]37 Apr 4; Binding, Rudolf Georg, 1867-1938; 1 item (3 p.); 23 cm. (Box GROUP 26, Folder F-1)
      ALS thanking Faber du Faur for his hospitality.
  - BRECHT, BERTOLT, 1898-1956
    - "An die Nachgeborenen", undated; Brecht, Bertolt, 1898-1956; 1 item (2 p.); 28 cm. (Box GROUP 13, Folder F-1)
      Poem, typescript carbon.
  - BROCH, HERMANN, 1886-1951
    - Letter: One Evelyn Place, Princeton, N.J., to [Hans Georg Franz] Aschaffenburg, 1946 Oct 20; Broch, Hermann, 1886-1951; 1 item (1 p.); 18 cm. (Box GROUP 41, Folder F-1)
      TLS to Aschaffenburg, whose pen name was George Amberg, regarding The Death of Virgil, and mentioning Erich Kahler.
      Accession: 20050726-h
  - BROD, MAX, 1884-1968
    - Letters: Tel Aviv, to Hans Demetz, 1962-63; Brod, Max, 1884-1968; 4 items. (Box GROUP 5, Folder F-1)
      Three TLS and one ALS mentioning his autobiography, his novel Mira, a Kafka conference, and Felix Weltsch, Hugo Bergmann, Ernst Taussig, Rudolf Fuchs and others.
      Accession: 19911210-b
- C
  - CLAUDY, FRANK, 1844-1919
    - Papers relating to "Prince Constant", 1907-31, undated; Claudy, Frank, 1844-1919; 34 items. (Box GROUP 37, Folder F-1-3)
      Drafts, notes and photographs relating to an 8-act play first performed on "Dec. 28, 1908." Two holograph drafts of play, one corrected and undated and one "Rewritten and remodeled" in April 1907, in notebook, with four printed advertisements for performances dating from 1909-13 tipped in. Loose notes include two holograph manuscripts, one titled "Prolog," one typescript carbon fragment and one autograph note, dated April 21, 1931, signed "Carl H. Claudy." Twenty-seven photographs of stage sets, some attributed to C. H. Claudy, and two photographs of groups of children.
  - CORRINTH, CURT, 1894-1960
    - Note: Hartelangenvorwerk bei Löwenberg/Schles[ien], to an unidentified recipient, 1923 Jan 4; Corrinth, Curt, 1894-1960; 1 item (1 p.); 9 x 11 cm. (Box GROUP 43, Folder F-1)
      ANS to "Herr Doktor" expressing thanks for a financial gift.
      Removed from: Gift by Curt Corrinth (Berlin: Budeju, 1923).
      Accession: 20020719-k
- E
  - EWALD, JOHANN JOACHIM, 1727-
    - Letter: to an indentified recipient, [1757?]; Ewald, Johann Joachim, 1727-; 1 item (2 p.); 24 cm. (Box GROUP 14, Folder F-1)
      ALS mentioning Gottlieb Wilhelm Rabener ("Steuersekretaer" at Dresden) and Christian Ludwig von Hagedorn ("Legationsrat und Generaldirektor der Kunstgalerie, Dresden").
      Includes note in contemporary hand: "1757. H. Ewald."
- F
  - FRANCKE, KUNO, 1855-1930
    - Letter: The Germanic Museum of Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass., to [Andrew J.?] Onderdonk, 1912 Jun 1; Francke, Kuno, 1855-1930; 1 item (3 leaves); 20 cm. (Box GROUP 16, Folder F-1)
      ALS concerning the identity of an unauthorized 1761 reprint of Magnus Gottfried Lichtwer's Vier Bücher Aesopischer Fabeln (1748).
      Removed from Auserlesene, verbesserte Fabeln und Erzählungen by Magnus Gottfried Lichtwer (Greifswald und Leipzig, 1761).
  - FREDERICK III, GERMAN EMPEROR, 1831-1888
    - Letter: to Voltaire, 1882; Frederick III, German Emperor, 1831-1888; 1 item (1 folded sheet); 29 cm. (Box GROUP 39, Folder F-1)
      ALS from Frederick III to Voltaire, in French, mentioning the Duke of Richelieu and Duke of Cumberland. Accompanied by ALS in German from R.[obert?] Dohme, dated "3 Juli 1882," to "Hochgeehrter Herr Graf," note in unidentified hand, and two seals.
      Accession: 20000103-m
  - FREY, EGON, 1892-
    - Corrections and annotations relating to Schakal: ein Kampf um die Zukunft: Roman, 1963 Mar; Frey, Egon, 1892-1972; 4 items. (Box GROUP 40, Folder F-1)
      Manuscript fragments, typescript carbon.
      Removed from Schakal: ein Kampf um die Zukunft: Roman (Hamburg: Gebru¨der Enoch, 1924).
      Accession: 20051003-h
    - Corrections and annotations relating to Der Zensor: Erza¨hlungen, 1962, 1969; Frey, Egon, 1892-1972; 2 items. (Box GROUP 40, Folder F-2)
      List of corrections and annotations and manuscript notes, typescript and holograph.
      Removed from Der Zensor: Erza¨hlungen (Hamburg: Gebru¨der Enoch, 1922.
      Accession: 20051003-g
  - FRIEDLAENDER, MAX, 1852-1934
    - Letter: to Gustav Gruener, New Haven, 1922 October 12; Friedlaender, Max, 1852-1934; 1 postcard. (Box GROUP 52, Folder F-1)
      Brief autograph letter, signed, referring to Goethe, with an unidentified music quotation.
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Source unknown.
      Accession: 46325
  - FÖRSTER-NIETZSCHE, ELISABETH, 1846-1935
    - Letter: Nietzsche-Archiv, Weimer, to an unidentified recipient, 1898 May 27; Förster-Nietzsche, Elisabeth, 1846-1935; 1 item (4 p.); 22 cm. (Box GROUP 15, Folder F-1)
      ALS to "Sehr geehrter Herr" concerning publication of her brother's works, particularly translations in England.
- G
  - GEIRINGER, GERTRUD
    - Photograph of Richard Beer-Hofmann, [1934 fall]; Geiringer, Gertrud; 1 photograph: b & w; 18 cm. (Box GROUP 54, Folder F-1)
      Photograph of Beer-Hofmann at Altaussee, Austria.
      Former call number: Zg20 Mss G31
  - GERSTÄCKER, FRIEDRICH, 1816-1872
    - Letter: Gotha, to Herr Reichardt, 1865 Oct 21; Gerstäcker, Friedrich, 1816-1872; 1 item (2 p.); 21 cm. (Box GROUP 17, Folder F-1)
      ALS requesting a decision on publication in the Herald of a work entitled "Nach 15 Jahren" by an unnamed friend, and stating the conditions under which it may be published.
      Removed from Der deutschen Auswanderer Fahrten und Schicksale by Friedrich Gerstäcker (Leipzig: F. A. Brockhaus, 1847).
  - GOLL, YVAN, 1891-1950
    - "Auction Sale in New Hampshire", undated; Goll, Yvan, 1891-1950; 1 item (2 leaves); 28 cm. (Box GROUP 18, Folder F-1)
      Poem, typescript, signed.
  - GRASS, GÜNTER, 1927-
    - Letter: Friedenau, am, Niedstrasse 13, D-1000 Berlin 41, to Joan Davies, 21 West 26th Street, New York, NY 10010, 1990 May 28; Grass, Günter, 1927-2015; 1 item (1 p.); 30 cm. (Box GROUP 33, Folder F-1)
      TLS recommending Gerhard Köpf, and mentioning Helen Wolff.
      Accession: 19981201-a
- H
  - HAGEDORN, EDUARD THEOBALT
    - Notebook, undated; Hagedorn, Eduard Theobalt; 1 v. ([34] p.); 10 x 13 cm. (Box GROUP 4, Folder F-1)
      Holograph manuscript in several hands, including poetry, excerpts from Goethe and Schiller, and financial notes.
  - HELL, THEODOR, 1775-1856
    - Letter: Dresden, to Karl von La Roche, Weimar, 1830 Dec 20; Hell, Theodor, 1775-1856; 1 item (2 p.); 26 cm. (Box GROUP 34, Folder F-4)
      ALS, with address leaf, signed "Winkler," concerning the German production of the opera "La dama soldato."
      Accession: 20030728-t
    - Letter: Desden, to an unidentified recipient, 1832 Apr 14; Hell, Theodor, 1775-1856; 1 item (1 p.); 13 x 19 cm. (Box GROUP 34, Folder F-1)
      ALS to "verehrter Freund," signed "K. Winkler," concerning contributions to the Dresden Abend-Zeitung and to Penelope.
      Accession: 19991115-i
    - Letter: to Louis Delâtre, [18]42 Nov 17; Hell, Theodor, 1775-1856; 1 item (1 folded sheet); 23 cm. (Box GROUP 34, Folder F-2)
      ALS, signed "Charles Winkler," discussing provision of a list of his works to Delâtre.
      Accession: 19991115-h
    - Letter: Dresden, to an unidentified recipient, 1853 Mar 13; Hell, Theodor, 1775-1856; 1 item (1 p.); 22 cm. (Box GROUP 34, Folder F-3)
      ALS to "Ew. Wohlgebohren," signed "Karl Winkler," concerning articles submitted to Household Words, edited by Charles Dickens.
      Accession: 19991115-g
  - HESSE, HERMANN, 1877-1962
    - Letters: to Walter Meckauer, 1946, undated; Hesse, Hermann, 1877-1962; 6 items. (Box GROUP 28, Folder F-1)
      Three ANS, one with envelope, and three typed notes signed. Accompanied by seven envelopes postmarked 1944-46, undated ANS with envelope, postmarked 1946 Dec 10, shows reproduction of photograph of Hesse and his grand-daughter. Two undated cards show view of Hesse's house at Montagnola.
    - "Aus dem Glasperlenspiel", undated; Hesse, Hermann, 1877-1962; 1 item (6 p.); 30 cm. (Box GROUP 28, Folder F-2)
      Poems, typescript carbon. Includes: "Aus Josef Knechts hinterlassenen Schriften: Klage"; "Der letzte Glasperlenspieler"; "Ein Traum"; "Seifenblasen"; "Stufen (Gegenstueck zu 'Klage')"; "Das Glasperlenspiel."
    - "Ein paar Gedanken aus meinen Schriften", 1951; Hesse, Hermann, 1877-1962; 1 v. ([17] p.); 21 cm. (Box GROUP 28, Folder F-3)
      Holograph manuscript in bound notebook. Inscribed to Bryher.
    - "In Sand geschrieben", undated; Hesse, Hermann, 1877-1962; 1 item (1 p.); 28 cm. (Box GROUP 28, Folder F-4)
      Poem, typescript carbon. With manuscript note from Henri Peyre to Carl F. Schreiber explaining that Peyre copied the poem from the 1947 Sep 27 issue of Literatur und Kunst.
    - "Kleiner Gesang", 1962 May; Hesse, Hermann, 1877-1962; 1 item (1 folded sheet); 16 cm. (Box GROUP 28, Folder F-5)
      Poem, typescript, signed, with watercolor drawing on cover. Envelope addressed to "Mrs." Bryher.
    - "Wanderer im Spätherbst", 1956; Hesse, Hermann, 1877-1962; 1 item (2 folded sheets); 23 cm. (Box GROUP 28, Folder F-6)
      Poem, typescript, corrected and signed, with watercolor drawing on front cover and inscription to H.D. on inside back cover.
    - "Zwei Gedichte", undated; Hesse, Hermann, 1877-1962; 1 v. ([12] leaves); 21 cm. (Box GROUP 28, Folder F-7)
      Poems, holograph, in bound notebook. With "Alter Maler in der Werkstatt" and "Licht der Frühe." Blank postcard of painting pasted down on inside front cover and photograph of Hesse pasted down on inside back cover. Inscribed to Bryher.
    - "Zwölf Gedichte", undated; Hesse, Hermann, 1877-1962; 1 item (13 folded sheets); 23 cm. (Box GROUP 28, Folder F-8)
      Poems, holograph, with watercolor drawings. Inscribed to Norman Holmes Pearson. With typescript mimeograph sheet laid in.
  - HESSE, OTTO ERNST, 1891-
    - Frühling in Franken: Komödie in sieben Bildern / von Otto Ernst Hesse, [1933?]; Hesse, Otto Ernst, 1891-; 1 v. ( 88 p.); 20 cm. (Box GROUP 48, Folder F-1)
      Typescript mimeograph, with printed title page (Berlin: Oesterheld, copyright 1933) and manuscript annotations; manuscript revisions laid in.
      On title page: Unverkäufliches Manuskript. Als Manuskript vervielfältigt.
      Preliminary page: Hergestellt durch Marita Hasenclever.
      Former call number: Zg20 Mss H59
  - HITLER, ADOLF, 1889-1945
    - Greeting card: München, to an unidentified recipient, 1940 Dec; Hitler, Adolf, 1889-1945; 1 item (1 p.); 12 x 20 cm. (Box GROUP 35, Folder F-1)
      Printed Christmas card and New Year's greeting, with printed signature and stamp.
      Accession: 20021007-e
  - HOERSCHELMANN, ROLF VON
    - Letter: Rouchi b. Marza, Villa Brugnoli, to Emma von Faber du Faur, undated; Hoerschelmann, Rolf von; 1 item (4 p.); 18 cm. (Box GROUP 27, Folder F-1)
      ALS thanking Faber du Faur for her hospitality.
  - HOFMANNSTHAL, HUGO VON, 1874-1929
    - Letters: to Alfred Freiherr von Berger, [1892?]-[1904?],undated; Hofmannsthal, Hugo von, 1874-1929; 9 items. (Box GROUP 51, Folder F-1)
      9 autograph letters, signed.
      Accompanied by typed transcripts and photocopies of published letters.
      Former call number: Zg20 Mss H67 B892
  - HUESSY, HANS R.
    - "Goethes Politische Ansichten", undated; Huessy, Hans R.; 1 item (41 leaves); 28 cm. (Box GROUP 3, Folder F-1)
      Typescript manuscript, corrected. Title on folder cover: "Goethe: Seine Politischen Ansichten."
      Accession: 19860102-k
- K
  - KOHUT, GEORGE ALEXANDER, 1874-1933
    - Letter: 302 West 87th Street, [New York], to [Arthur Hubbell] Palmer, Department of German Literature, Yale University, New Haven, Conn., 1917 Jun 4; Kohut, George Alexander, 1874-1933; 1 item (2 p.); 18 cm. (Box GROUP 20, Folder F-1)
      TLS, with envelope, asking Palmer to review Kohut's edition of Lessing's Nathan the Wise.
      Removed from Nathan the Wise by Gotthold Ephraim Lessing (New York: Block Publishing Company, 1917).
  - KRÜGER, HERMAN ANDERS, 1871-1945
    - Portrait of Herman Anders Krüger, undated; Krüger, Herman Anders, 1871-1945; 1 print: b & w; 14 cm. (Box GROUP 53, Folder F-1)
      Print, inscribed to an unidentified fellow scholar, possibly a member of the Yale University Department of Germanic Languages faculty.
      Accession: 46327
  - KURT WOLFF VERLAG
    - Letters: to Wilhelm Haas, 1914-17; Kurt Wolff Verlag; 10 items. (Box GROUP 38, Folder F-1)
      Eight TLS from Kurt Wolff Verlag and two APcS from Kurt Wolff. Letters discuss a Rodin manuscript translation and the military effort against the Serbs in Czechoslovakia, mentioning Mr. [Kurt] Wolff, Dr. Ramler, Sternheim, Scheler, Hedwig Bergmann, René Schickele and others. Includes enevelope.
      Accession: 20030717-g
- L
  - LENAU, NICOLAUS, 1802-1850
    - Faust, undated; Lenau, Nicolaus, 1802-1850; 1 item (2 p.); 27 cm. (Box GROUP 21, Folder F-1)
      Holograph fragment of scene entitled "Görg."
      Includes note of authentication, dated "7 Mai 1859," by Lenau's brother-in-law, Ant.[on] X.[avier] Schurz.
- M
  - MANN, THOMAS, 1875-1955
    - Autograph, 1950 Apr 3; Mann, Thomas, 1875-1955; 1 item (1 p.); 6 x 12 cm. (Box GROUP 47, Folder F-1)
      Autograph clipped from note (not present), inscribed "with kindest personal regards" and dated "Pacific Palisades, 3 Apr. 1950." Framed with printed reproduction.
      Accession: 30893
  - MUMFORD, LEWIS, 1895-
    - Letters: New York, 1941; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-1990; 2 items. (Box GROUP 9, Folder F-1)
      One TLS to [Hermann] Broch, dated 1941 Sep 15, concerning a luncheon planned with Martha Foley and Beatrice Kaufman on the situation in France, mentioning Janet Flanner, Kay Boyle, Hans Habe, Dr. Frank Kingdon and others. One ALS to [Annemarie Meier-Graefe], addressed to "Dear Bush," concerning a debate with Sinclair Lewis.
      Accession: 19950701-hw
  - MÜLLER, HANS VON, 1875-1944
    - Letters: Berlin, to Hans Huth, 1910-29; Müller, Hans Von, 1875-1944; 15 items. (Box GROUP 22, Folder F-1)
      Six ALS, five ANS, and four autograph postcards signed. Includes four envelopes.
- N
  - NADLER, JOSEF, 1884-1963
    - Letters: Wien, to [Walter Rehm], 1957; Nadler, Josef, 1884-1963; 2 items. (Box GROUP 2, Folder F-1)
      Two TLS. Accompanied by typescript letter, dated 1988 Dec 21, from Ingeborg Harms to Christa Sammons.
      Accession: 19881221-be
  - NEUMANN, ROBERT, 1897-1975
    - Letter: House 14, Mooragh Detention Camp, Ramsey, Isle of Man, to Hermann Broch, 11 Alexander Street, Princeton, N.J., [19]40 Jun 13; Neumann, Robert, 1897-1975; 1 item (postcard); 9 x 14 cm. (Box GROUP 32, Folder F-1)
      Autograph postcard signed regarding possible lecture tour in U.S.
      Accession: 19980813-c
  - NIEBUHR, [MARCUS VON, 1817-1860?]
    - Letter: Char[lottenburg?], to an unidentified recipient, [18]54 Dec 13; Niebuhr, [Marcus von, 1817-1860?]; 1 item (2 p.); 23 cm. (Box GROUP 25, Folder F-1)
      ALS to an unidentified senator concerning the possibility of undesirable elements entering the Irvingite sect [i.e. Catholic Apostolic Church].
- P
  - PANTHEON BOOKS
    - Papers relating to history of Pantheon Books, 1942-62, undated; Pantheon Books; 1 folder. (Box GROUP 10, Folder F-1)
      Papers include letters, contracts and manuscript notes. Letters include one TLS from Kurt Wolff to Kyrill Schabert, dated 1942 Oct 1, Schabert's reply, in carbon, and one TL carbon, dated 1962 Aug 10, from Paula Van Doren and Andre Schiffrin of Pantheon Books to Bennett Cerf and Donald Klopfer of Random House. Contracts and manuscript notes include: holograph manuscript production list for 1943-59; photocopy of typed contract, dated 1961 Jul 27, between Pantheon Books and Bollingen Foundation; undated press release; typed carbon history; and holograph notes.
      Accession: 19961107-f
- S
  - SACHS, NELLY
    - Letter: Bergsundsstrand 23, 11738 Stockholm, Sverige, to Jean Starr Untermeyer, 235 East 73rd Street, New York, [19]68 Oct 25; Sachs, Nelly; 1 item (2 p.); 28 cm. (Box GROUP 8, Folder F-1)
      ALS, with address leaf, expressing thanks for a book.
  - SCHMIDT, MARGARETE
    - Letter: to an unidentified recipient, 1960 Dec; Schmidt, Margarete; 1 item (1 p.); 11 x 15 cm. (Box GROUP 30, Folder F-1)
      ALS (fragment), possibly to Hermann Hesse, regarding his work.
  - SCHÜBEL, THEODOR, 1925-
    - Note: Freiberg im Breisgau, to Hermann Hesse, Montagnola, [19]61 Mar 29; Schübel, Theodor, 1925-; 1 item (postcard); 11 x 15 cm. (Box GROUP 31, Folder F-1)
      Autograph postcard signed regarding Hesse's work.
  - SEYDEL, GERHARD
    - Letters: to Yale University, 1949 April-December; Seydel, Gerhard; 4 items. (Box GROUP 49, Folder F-1)
      4 typed letters, signed, about donations of manuscripts of his plays and poems to the Yale University Library. One letter encloses copies of letters to the New York Times.
      Former call number: Zg20 Mss Se52 949
    - Hadu und Hatto: Schauspiel in 3 Aufzugen, 1947-1948; Seydel, Gerhard; 2 items. (Box GROUP 49, Folder F-2, Folder F-3)
      Play, two versions, typescript carbon.
      Title from covers.
      Former call number: Zg20 Mss Se52 947
    - Hamilcus: Drama in einem Aufzug, [1918]; Seydel, Gerhard; 1 item (18 p.); 19 cm. (Box GROUP 49, Folder F-4)
      Play, autograph manuscript.
      Title from cover.
      Accompanied by a typed transcript and notes about the play by "Dr. Pfeiffer," copy, typescript, signed by Seydel.
      Former call number: Zg20 Mss Se52 918
    - Konradin: Trauerspiel in vier Aufzugen, 1948 summer; Seydel, Gerhard; 1 v. (123 p.); 35 cm. (Box GROUP 49, Folder F-5)
      Appended and laid in: poems, autograph manuscript, 1944 February-1949 March.
      Affixed to inside back cover: photograph of Seydel, with his wife, Lisa Seydel, and daughter, Ursula Seydel.
      Former call number: Zg20 Mss Se52 948
    - Poems, 1949-1950; Seydel, Gerhard; 4 items. (Box GROUP 49, Folder F-6)
      Poems, autograph manuscript, signed. Titles: "Auf amerikanischem Ozean," "Ich hab's mit mir faustdick," "Prolog," and "Schlummerlied."
  - SORGE, SUSANNE M.
    - Letters: Flüelen, Switzerland, to Albert Muenst, Einsiedeln, Switzerland, 1924 Ocober-1925 February; Sorge, Susanne M.; 3 items. (Box GROUP 56, Folder F-1)
      3 autograph letters, signed, about writings of Sorge's husband, Reinhard Johannes Sorge.
      Accompanied by 2 manuscript prayer cards, undated, in German and French.
      Former call number: Uncat Zg Ms 31
      Accession: 19970917-ak
  - STAIGER, EMIL, 1908-
    - Letter: Zürich 32 Witikonerstrasse 77, to [Walter] Rehm, [19]49 Oct 11; Staiger, Emil, 1908-; 1 item (2 p.); 30 cm. (Box GROUP 1, Folder F-1)
      TLS mentioning Goethe, Hölderlin, Kierkegaard and Heidegger. Accompanied by typescript letter, dated 1988 Dec 21, from Ingeborg Harms to Christa Sammons.
      Accession: 19881221-bf
  - STERN'SCHES KONSERVATORIUM
    - Receipt, 1919 Mar; Stern'sches Konservatorium; 1 item (1 p.); 11 x 14 cm. (Box GROUP 44, Folder F-1)
      Receipt made out to Fritz Klebbs for the month of March, 1919, signed.
      Removed from Das Wedekindbuch: herausgegeben und mit einer Monographie von Joachim Friedenthal (München: Georg Müller, 1914).
      Accession: 20040610-ct
- T
  - TORBERG, FRIEDRICH, 1908-
    - "Die Einschlaeferung Noahs", undated; Torberg, Friedrich, 1908-; 1 item (4 leaves); 28 cm. (Box GROUP 19, Folder F-1)
      Typescript carbon excerpt, corrected, from Torberg's PPP: Pamphlete, Parodien, Post Scripta, a parody of Thomas Mann's Joseph novels.
    - "Sehnsucht Nach Altaussee", 1942; Torberg, Friedrich, 1908-; 1 item (2 p.); 27 cm. (Box GROUP 19, Folder F-2)
      Poem, typescript, written for Gertrude Geiringer.
  - TUREL, ADRIEN, 1890-1957
    - Papers, 1954, undated; Turel, Adrien, 1890-1957; 4 items. (Box GROUP 42, Folder F-1)
      Papers include: one ALS from Turel to "Herr D. Kutter"; one page of text relating to Dante and Hamlet, typescript, possibly excerpted from Turel's Eros Demiurgos; printed dealer's list for Turel's Ecce Superhomo, including other titles; and a catalog fragment.
      Accession: 20051201-y
- U
  - UNIDENTIFIED
    - Pharmaceutical recipe, undated; Unidentified; 1 item (1 p.); 10 x 14 cm. (Box GROUP 29, Folder F-1)
      Manuscript from late 18th or early 19th century.